const questions = [
    {
        question: "In which of the following, a person is constantly followed/chased by another person or group of several peoples ?",
        optionA: "Phishing",
        optionB: "Bulling",
        optionC: "Stalking",
        optionD: "Identity theft",
        correctOption: "optionC"
    },

    {
        question: " Which one of the following can be considered as the class of computer threats ?",
        optionA: "Dos Attack",
        optionB: "Phising",
        optionC: "Binary 101 Virus",
        optionD: "Hecker :|",
        correctOption: "optionA"
    },

    {
        question: "Which of the following is considered as the unsolicited commercial email ?",
        optionA: "http://abc.mail.xyz",
        optionB: "Yahoo",
        optionC: "Proton Mail",
        optionD: "Spam",
        correctOption: "optionD"
    },

    {
        question: "Which of the following usually observe each activity on the internet of the victim, gather all information in the background, and send it to someone else ?",
        optionA: "COVID 19",
        optionB: "A Virus with eyes",
        optionC: "Spyware",
        optionD: "Cortona",
        correctOption: "optionC"
    },

    {
        question: "_______ is a type of software designed to help the user's computer detect viruses and avoid them.",
        optionA: "Savier of your Computer!",
        optionB: "A hacker",
        optionC: "js.html.css.php.com.io.net.org",
        optionD: "AntiVirus",
        correctOption: "optionD"
    },

    {
        question: "Which one of the following is a type of antivirus program ?",
        optionA: "Quick heal",
        optionB: "Mcafee",
        optionC: "Kaspersky",
        optionD: "All of the above",
        correctOption: "optionD"
    },

    {
        question: "It can be a software program or a hardware device that filters all data packets coming through the internet, a network, etc. it is known as the_______:",
        optionA: "AntiOxident",
        optionB: "QuickVirus",
        optionC: "Firewall",
        optionD: "All of the above",
        correctOption: "optionC"
    },

    {
        question: "Which of the following refers to stealing one's idea or invention of others and use it for their own benefits ?",
        optionA: "Plagiarism",
        optionB: "Show Answers",
        optionC: "Flag/Report this question",
        optionD: "None of the above",
        correctOption: "optionA"
    },

    {
        question: "Binary consists of which of the following numbers ?",
        optionA: "1",
        optionB: "Zero",
        optionC: "One",
        optionD: "All of the above",
        correctOption: "optionD"
    },

    {
        question: `Which of the following refers to exploring the appropriate, ethical behaviors related to the online environment and digital media platform ?`,
        optionA: "Cyber Habits",
        optionB: "OnlineInstructs.com",
        optionC: "Cyberethics",
        optionD: "Computer Rules",
        correctOption: "optionC"
    },

    {
        question: "Which one of the following refers to the technique used for verifying the integrity of the message ?",
        optionA: "Message Grits",
        optionB: "InterGrits",
        optionC: "Message Digest",
        optionD: "MessageTech.xyz.com.net.io.org",
        correctOption: "optionC"
    },

    {
        question: "Which one of the following usually used in the process of Wi-Fi-hacking ?",
        optionA: "Aircrack-ng",
        optionB: "WiFiHacks",
        optionC: "Aircracking",
        optionD: "Proton",
        correctOption: "optionA"
    },


    {
        question: "Which of the following is not a type of scanning ?",
        optionA: "Xmas Tree Scan",
        optionB: "Cloud Scan",
        optionC: "Null Scan",
        optionD: "SYN Stealth",
        correctOption: "optionB"
    },

    {
        question: "Which one of the following is actually considered as the first computer virus ?",
        optionA: "aws.spidervirus.hk",
        optionB: "Version666",
        optionC: "Null:404",
        optionD: "Creeper",
        correctOption: "optionD"
    },

    {
        question: "Code Red is a type of ________",
        optionA: "A computer Virus",
        optionB: "V1018 Version v.1.8",
        optionC: "Firewall",
        optionD: "Antivirus",
        correctOption: "optionA"
    },

    {
        question: "Which one of the following is also referred to as malicious software ?",
        optionA: "Maliciousware",
        optionB: "Ilegalware",
        optionC: "Malware",
        optionD: "Nurton",
        correctOption: "optionC"
    },

    {
        question: "Hackers usually used the computer virus for ______ purpose.",
        optionA: "To log, monitor each and every user's stroke",
        optionB: "To gain access the sensitive information like user's Id and Passwords",
        optionC: "To corrupt the user's data stored in the computer system",
        optionD: "All of the above",
        correctOption: "optionD"
    },

    {
        question: "When was the first computer virus created ?",
        optionA: "2009",
        optionB: "1971",
        optionC: "1970",
        optionD: "2096",
        correctOption: "optionC"
    },

    {
        question: "Which of the following is considered as the world's first antivirus program ?",
        optionA: "Creeper",
        optionB: "AntiVirus",
        optionC: "MacAdFree",
        optionD: "Reaper",
        correctOption: "optionD"
    },

    {
        question: "Which type of the following malware does not replicate or clone them self's through infection ?",
        optionA: "Trojans",
        optionB: "Worms",
        optionC: "Viruses",
        optionD: "Insects",
        correctOption: "optionA"
    },

    {
        question: "Which of the following malware's type allows the attacker to access the administrative controls and enables his/or her to do almost anything he wants to do with the infected computers.",
        optionA: "MOUSEs",
        optionB: "TMs",
        optionC: "@17#$",
        optionD: "RATs",
        correctOption: "optionD"
    },

    {
        question: "Which of the following is a type of independent malicious program that never required any host program ?",
        optionA: "ZombiesTATs",
        optionB: "Worm",
        optionC: "VenusFlyTRAPtm",
        optionD: "Virus:CODEred",
        correctOption: "optionB"
    },

    {
        question: " In order to ensure the security of the data/ information, we need to ____________ the data.",
        optionA: "Password-Lock",
        optionB: "Encrypt",
        optionC: "FireWall",
        optionD: "Delete/Remove",
        correctOption: "optionB"
    },

    {
        question: "Which of the following is considered as the first hacker's conference ?",
        optionA: "ORSCOPE",
        optionB: "HACKERConsole",
        optionC: "DEFCON",
        optionD: "OSCON",
        correctOption: "optionC"
    },

    {
        question: "Which of the following known as the oldest phone hacking techniques used by hackers to make free calls?",
        optionA: "Phishing",
        optionB: "Cracking",
        optionC: "Phreaking",
        optionD: "Hacking",
        correctOption: "optionC"
    }

]


let shuffledQuestions = [] //empty array to hold shuffled selected questions

function handleQuestions() { 
    //function to shuffle and push 10 questions to shuffledQuestions array
    while (shuffledQuestions.length <= 9) {
        const random = questions[Math.floor(Math.random() * questions.length)]
        if (!shuffledQuestions.includes(random)) {
            shuffledQuestions.push(random)
        }
    }
}


let questionNumber = 1
let playerScore = 0  
let wrongAttempt = 0 
let indexNumber = 0

// function for displaying next question in the array to dom
function NextQuestion(index) {
    handleQuestions()
    const currentQuestion = shuffledQuestions[index]
    document.getElementById("question-number").innerHTML = questionNumber
    document.getElementById("player-score").innerHTML = playerScore
    document.getElementById("display-question").innerHTML = currentQuestion.question;
    document.getElementById("option-one-label").innerHTML = currentQuestion.optionA;
    document.getElementById("option-two-label").innerHTML = currentQuestion.optionB;
    document.getElementById("option-three-label").innerHTML = currentQuestion.optionC;
    document.getElementById("option-four-label").innerHTML = currentQuestion.optionD;

}


function checkForAnswer() {
    const currentQuestion = shuffledQuestions[indexNumber] //gets current Question 
    const currentQuestionAnswer = currentQuestion.correctOption //gets current Question's answer
    const options = document.getElementsByName("option"); //gets all elements in dom with name of 'option' (in this the radio inputs)
    let correctOption = null

    options.forEach((option) => {
        if (option.value === currentQuestionAnswer) {
            //get's correct's radio input with correct answer
            correctOption = option.labels[0].id
        }
    })
   
    //checking to make sure a radio input has been checked or an option being chosen
    if (options[0].checked === false && options[1].checked === false && options[2].checked === false && options[3].checked == false) {
        document.getElementById('option-modal').style.display = "flex"
    }

    //checking if checked radio button is same as answer
    options.forEach((option) => {
        if (option.checked === true && option.value === currentQuestionAnswer) {
            document.getElementById(correctOption).style.backgroundColor = "green"
            playerScore++
            indexNumber++
            //set to delay question number till when next question loads
            setTimeout(() => {
                questionNumber++
            }, 1000)
        }

        else if (option.checked && option.value !== currentQuestionAnswer) {
            const wrongLabelId = option.labels[0].id
            document.getElementById(wrongLabelId).style.backgroundColor = "red"
            document.getElementById(correctOption).style.backgroundColor = "green"
            wrongAttempt++
            indexNumber++
            //set to delay question number till when next question loads
            setTimeout(() => {
                questionNumber++
            }, 1000)
        }
    })
}



//called when the next button is called
function handleNextQuestion() {
    checkForAnswer()
    unCheckRadioButtons()
    //delays next question displaying for a second
    setTimeout(() => {
        if (indexNumber <= 9) {
            NextQuestion(indexNumber)
        }
        else {
            handleEndGame()
        }
        resetOptionBackground()
    }, 1000);
}

//sets options background back to null after display the right/wrong colors
function resetOptionBackground() {
    const options = document.getElementsByName("option");
    options.forEach((option) => {
        document.getElementById(option.labels[0].id).style.backgroundColor = ""
    })
}

// unchecking all radio buttons for next question(can be done with map or foreach loop also)
function unCheckRadioButtons() {
    const options = document.getElementsByName("option");
    for (let i = 0; i < options.length; i++) {
        options[i].checked = false;
    }
}

// function for when all questions being answered
function handleEndGame() {
    let remark = null
    let remarkColor = null

    // condition check for player remark and remark color
    if (playerScore <= 3) {
        remark = "Bad Grades, Keep Practicing."
        remarkColor = "red"
    }
    else if (playerScore >= 4 && playerScore < 7) {
        remark = "Average Grades, You can do better."
        remarkColor = "orange"
    }
    else if (playerScore >= 7) {
        remark = "Excellent, Keep the good work going."
        remarkColor = "green"
    }
    const playerGrade = (playerScore / 10) * 100

    //data to display to score board
    document.getElementById('remarks').innerHTML = remark
    document.getElementById('remarks').style.color = remarkColor
    document.getElementById('grade-percentage').innerHTML = playerGrade
    document.getElementById('wrong-answers').innerHTML = wrongAttempt
    document.getElementById('right-answers').innerHTML = playerScore
    document.getElementById('score-modal').style.display = "flex"

}

//closes score modal and resets game
function closeScoreModal() {
    questionNumber = 1
    playerScore = 0
    wrongAttempt = 0
    indexNumber = 0
    shuffledQuestions = []
    NextQuestion(indexNumber)
    document.getElementById('score-modal').style.display = "none"
}

//function to close warning modal
function closeOptionModal() {
    document.getElementById('option-modal').style.display = "none"
}